Boston, Mass. Berkeley Temple Congregational Church records, 1827-1907.
Congregational Library & Archives
Boston, Mass. Berkeley Temple Congregational Church records, 1827-1907.
RG0029
Congregational Library & Archives
3.32 Cubic Feet
(5 boxes)
The Pine Street Church was formed in 1827. In April of 1857, the Committee of the Pine Street Church met to discuss the sale of the church's property. The church building was later sold in July of 1857. After the sale of the building, the Pine Street Church and Society purchased land for a new church building at the intersection of Berkeley Street and Warren Avenue in the South End of Boston. By 1861, the new church was completed and had changed its name to the Berkeley Street Church. In 1887, the Berkeley Street Church changed their name to Berkeley Temple. In 1904, the name of the church was changed once more to Berkeley Temple Congregational Church. At the suggestion of an ecclesiastical council, the Berkeley Temple Congregational Church merged with the Union Congregational Church in 1907, which later merged with the Old South Church in 1948. This collection includes church records of administrative and vital records, including church registers, correspondence, pew tax records, committee reports, and cash ledgers. The collection also includes community records such as Sunday school minute and roll books, ecclesiastical council letters, circulars, and a scrapbook.
Berkeley Street Church (Boston, Mass.)
Berkeley Temple (Boston, Mass.)
Berkeley Temple Congregational Church (Boston, Mass.)
Pine Street Church (Boston, Mass.)
Arrangement
The Berkeley Temple Congregational Church records have been arranged into two series listed below. Series 1 has been further divided into 2 sub-series, and series 2 has been divided into 3 sub-series. Records in each series and sub-series have been primarily arranged chronologically by start date, and secondarily by topic.
Series 1: Church records, 1827-1907
Subseries 1: Administrative records, 1827-1907
Subseries 2: Vital records, 1827-1906
Series 2: Church Community records, 1836-1906
Subseries 1: Sunday school records, 1836-1906
Subseries 2: Ecclesiastic council records, 1845-1906
Subseries 3: Church programming and events, 1867-1906
Historical Note
The Pine Street Church was formed in 1827 in Boston by the then five Orthodox Congregational Churches, those being Old South Church, Park St. Church, Essex St. Church, Green St. Church, and the Hanover St. Church, who voted to build two new meeting houses with the goal of expanding religious influence in the city. One meeting house was located in the North End and the other in the South End at the corner of Pine Street and Washington Street, which would later become the Pine Street Church. $30,000 was raised to fund the construction; unfortunately the funds raised were insufficient to cover the costs of both buildings. After the funds were split between the churches, both meeting houses were forced to take on over $20,000 of debt to complete construction. When the Pine Street Church was formed in September of 1827, just months after the building was completed, the forty two members of the church took on the debt that came with the construction of the building at the recommendation of the founding churches. The Pine Street Church had difficulties retaining members and pastors alike due, in part, to the difficulties the church faced managing their debt. After a failed attempt to renovate and lease a portion of the meeting house in 1851, the debt had climbed to over $30,000. With few options left, in April of 1857, the five founding churches that had initiated its construction and the Committee of the Pine Street Church met to discuss the sale of the church's property. The church building was sold just months later in July of 1857. With the sale of the building, the Pine Street Church and Society was able to eliminate their debt and secure the funds necessary to purchase land for a new church building at the intersection of Berkeley Street and Warren Avenue in the South End of Boston. By 1861, the new church was completed and had changed its name to the Berkeley Street Church. In 1888, the Berkeley Street Church changed their name to Berkeley Temple. Free from their debt troubles, the church was able to eliminate the pew taxes that they had formerly relied on to pay expenses. The much larger church building was able to accommodate a growing number of members, as well as its Sunday school. They were able to increase their influence and membership by sending out circulars, as well as canvassing efforts in surrounding neighborhoods. They also promoted other church activities such as the Young Men's Institute and various classes on arithmetic, grammar, typewriting, and more, which were offered to men and women alike. In 1904, the name of the church was changed to Berkeley Temple Congregational Church. At the suggestion of the ecclesiastical council, the Berkeley Temple Congregational Church merged with the Union Congregational Church in 1907, which later merged with the Old South Church in 1948.
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
No acquisition information is available for this collection.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials relating to the Berkeley Temple Congregational Church in Boston. The collection includes records of the church and it's community, including administrative records such as pew tax records, cash ledgers, and examining committee records. The vital records include church registers, membership lists, and a necrology. The community records of this collection include Sunday school records, which contain minutes, rolls, and receiving books. The ecclesistic council materials contain correspondence and documents regarding the continued involment of an ecclesistic council with church affairs and community from 1845-1906. The church programming and events materials contain bulletins, circulars, a print, and a scrapbook which detail annual and special events at the church.
Bibliography
Committee of the Pine St. Society.A Church for the Masses in Boston. Boston: Press of Edward L. Balch, 1858. 7.11.1 B65.5 BerTC
Dickinson, Charles.The work of Berkeley Temple, Boston, organized for city evangelization, Christian nurture, practical Christianity. Boston, 1888. 7.11.1 B65.5 BerTC
Baptismal records.; Church correspondence.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church property.; Church records and registers.; Marriage records.; Necrologies.; Pews and pew rights.; Sunday schools.; Berkeley Street Church (Boston, Mass.); Berkeley Temple (Boston, Mass.); Berkeley Temple Congregational Church (Boston, Mass.); Pine Street Church (Boston, Mass.)
- Church records, 1827 1907; 1827-1907; 20 Folders; 21 Volumes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains administrative records and vital records of the Berkeley Temple Congregational Church. Administrative records include financial records, pew plans and records, committee reports, and general society correspondence. The vital records include church registers, membership and dismissal documents, membership applications, and a necrology.
  - Administrative records, 1827 1907; 1827-1907; 15 Folders; 16 Volumes
    This sub-series contains administrative records from the Berkeley Temple Congregational Church including general society documents and correspondence, pew tax records, financial ledgers, deeds, Examining Committee records and reports, and general church record books.
    - General society materials, 1827 1830; 1827-1830 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Church records, 1827 1861; 1827-1861 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    - General society materials, 1830 1831; 1830-1831 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - General society materials, 1832 1844; 1832-1844 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - General society materials, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - General society materials, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - General society materials, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - General society materials, 1858 1859; 1858-1859 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - General society materials, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - General society materials, 1861 1862; 1861-1862 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Pew proprietors and transfers, 1828 1864; 1828-1864 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Pew purchase and tax record, 1830 1839; 1830-1839 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    - Pew tax records, 1830 1857; 1830-1857 (Box 3, Volume 1)
    - Pew tax records, 1833 1839; 1833-1839 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    - Pew payment receipts, 1851 1857; 1851-1857 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Pew plans, 1856 1877; 1856, 1877, undated (Folder 2)
    - Deeds, 1827 1853; 1827-1853 (Folder 1)
    - Pine Street Association deed records, 1839 1857; 1839-1857 (Box 2, Volume 2)
    - Prudential committee records, 1848 1864; 1848-1864 (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - Examining committee special meetings, 1849 1867; 1849-1867 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Examining committee records, 1850 1858; 1850-1858 (Box 1, Volume 4)
    - Examining committee reports, 1853 1870; 1853-1870 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Examining committee records, 1858 1866; 1858-1866 (Box 1, Volume 6)
    - Constitution and records of Pine Street Association, 1857 1864; 1857-1864 (Box 1, Volume 5)
    - Church records, 1861 1887; 1861-1887 (Box 2, Volume 3)
    - Cash ledger, 1881 1882; 1881-1882 (Box 2, Volume 4)
    - Berkeley Temple pew records, 1882 1883; 1882-1883 (Box 2, Volume 7)
    - Cash ledger, 1882 1885; 1882-1885 (Box 2, Volume 5)
    - Cash ledger, 1886 1888; 1886-1888 (Box 2, Volume 6)
    - Cash book, 1891 1897; 1891-1897 (Box 1, Volume 7)
    - Church reports, 1901 1907; 1901-1907 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Cash ledger, 1906 1907; 1906-1907 (Box 1, Volume 8)
    - Acceptance and resignation letters, 1849 1901; 1849-1901 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Vital records, 1827 1906; 1827-1906; 6 Folders; 5 Volumes
    This sub-series contains vital records of the Berkeley Temple Congregational Church including membership records, church registrers, admittance, dissmissal, and transfer documents, a handwritten necrology, and the correspendence pertaining to the purhcase of the formerly enslaved John Henson's freedom.
    - Church register, 1827 1843; 1827-1843 (Box 1, Volume 9)
    - Church register, 1827 1853; 1827-1853 (Box 1, Volume 10)
    - Articles of faith and member list, 1842 (Box 4, Volume 7)
    - Transfer requests, 1845 1906; 1845-1906 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Membership and attendance reports, 1846 1868; 1846-1868 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Dismissal documents, 1848 1873; 1848-1873 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Membership record, 1851 (Box 1, Volume 11)
    - John Henson purchase, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Reverend Wright necrologies, 1861 1867; 1861-1867 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Church register, 1889 1895; 1889-1895 (Box 3, Volume 3)
    - Membership applications, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Church community records, 1836 1906; 1836-1906; 18 Folders; 14 Volumes
  This series contains community records for the Berkeley Temple Congregational Church, including Sunday school roll and minute books, ecclesiastical council letters, circulars, bulletins, and a scrapbook.
  - Sunday school records, 1836 1906; 1836-1906; 13 Volumes; 2 Folders
    This sub-series contains records of the Sunday school at Berkeley Temple Congregational Church, including roll books, minute books, recieiving books, lesson record books, and annual reports.
    - Sunday school minute book, 1836 1837; 1836-1837 (Box 1, Volume 12)
    - Sunday school receiving book, 1836 1839; 1836-1839 (Box 4, Volume 1)
    - Sunday school minute book, 1838 1839; 1838-1839 (Box 1, Volume 13)
    - Sunday school receiving book, 1839 (Box 1, Volume 14)
    - Sunday school annual reports, 1839 1906; 1839-1906 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Sunday school minute book, 1840 1841; 1840-1841 (Box 1, Volume 15)
    - Sunday school minute book, 1846 1847; 1846-1847 (Box 1, Volume 16)
    - Record of Pine Street Sabbath school, 1848 1851; 1848-1851 (Box 4, Volume 2)
    - Record of Pine Street School, 1853 1863; 1853-1863 (Box 3, Volume 2)
    - Sunday school roll book, 1857 (Box 4, Volume 3)
    - Sunday school roll book, 1858 (Box 4, Volume 4)
    - Sunday school roll book, 1859 (Box 4, Volume 5)
    - Sunday school anniversary, 1860 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Sunday school roll book, 1860 (Box 4, Volume 6)
    - Sunday school roll book, 1861 (Box 5, Volume 1)
  - Ecclesiastic council records, 1845 1906; 1845-1906; 11 Folders
    This sub-series contains letters and documents pertaining to the ecclesiastical council that Berkeley Temple Congregational Church was part of.
    - Ecclesiastical council letters, 1845 1849; 1845-1849 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Ecclesiastical council letters, 1850 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Ecclesiastical council letters, 1851 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Ecclesiastical council letters, 1852 1853; 1852-1853 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Ecclesiastical council letters, 1854 1855; 1854-1855 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Ecclesiastical council letters, 1856 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Ecclesiastical council letters, 1857 1867; 1857-1867 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Ecclesiastical council letters, 1867 1868; 1867-1868 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Ecclesiastical council letters, 1869 1871; 1869-1871 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Ecclesiastical council letters, 1873 1876; 1873-1876 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Ecclesiastical council letters, 1878 1906; 1878-1906 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Church programming and events, 1867 1906; 1867-1906; 5 Folders; 1 Volume
    This sub-series contains church programming and event materials, including circulars, bulletins, a scrapbook, and week of prayer and semi-centennial celebration materials.
    - Church circulars, 1867 1882; 1867-1882 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Berkeley Street Church scrapbook, 1868 1879; 1868-1879 (Box 1, Volume 17)
    - Semi-centennial celebration, 1876 1877; 1876-1877 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Week of prayer, 1876 1878; 1876-1878 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Church bulletins, 1906 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Print of church, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)